Okay, today's דף daf is נב Nun Bet 52. We start at
the bottom of נא עמוד ב Nun Aleph Amud Bet and we
start with right after the parentheses. So it's four lines before the
lines get wide. Exactly, okay.
אמר אמימר משמיה דרב דימי מנהרדעא. Amar Amemar mishmei deRav Dimi miNehardea.
So Amemar said in the name of Rav Dimi from Nehardea. You'll
remember we were talking about, we introduced the idea which had not
been in the earlier discussions that if this animal that falls off
the roof gets up and walks around, it's okay. If it waits
twenty-four hours or if it stands up without walking around, then it's
okay but you need to do an internal check. You need בדיקה.
bedikah. So what is that בדיקה bedikah for? So רש"י Rashi earlier
assumed the בדיקה bedikah was for the things that immediately affect the
bones because the גמרא Gemara sometimes talks about פירק עצמות, piruk atzamot,
so like the, you know, sort of like the bones are loosened.
רש"י Rashi said the checking was for to see if the ribs
had shattered because that is a separate טריפה, treifa, shattered ribs, or
if the spinal cord had severed. That's a specific טריפה. treifa. So
that's again, you solved the problem of פירק עצמות piruk atzamot by
itself which is seen as an independent טריפה treifa because it lived
or it stood up. Now you have to check for the other
טריפות. treifot. So what now the גמרא Gemara is going to address
itself to exactly what are those things you're checking for? So let's
take a look. אמר אמימר משמיה דרב דימי מנהרדעא. Amar Amemar mishmei
deRav Dimi miNehardea. So Amemar said in the name of Rav Dimi
from Nehardea נפולה שאמרו צריכה בדיקה, nefulah she'amru tzrichah bedikah,
when this fallen thing has to be checked, like I said, if
it stood up or it waited twenty-four hours, so it's okay as
long as you check it. What are you checking for? כנגד בני
מעי. keneged bnei mei'ayim. You're checking the internal organs to make sure
that they did not get a hole or a tear in this
fall. That makes a lot of sense. אמר ליה מר זוטרא. Amar
leh Mar Zutra. So מר זוטרא Mar Zutra said back to him
הכי אמרי משמיה דרב פפא. hachi amri mishmei deRav Pappa. Here's what
we say in the name of רב פפא, Rav Pappa, צריכה בדיקה
כנגד כל בית חלל כולו. tzrichah bedikah keneged kol beit halal kulo.
You have to check the entire inner cavity. Now what does that
mean? Not just the בני מעי, bnei mei'ayim, not just the בני
מעי bnei mei'ayim which are more like the digestive organs, but maybe
does it mean all of the organs including heart and lungs etc?
That could be. That's what I would assume. בית חלל beit halal
sounds like it's the cavity so it's everything in the cavity. Right?
רש"י Rashi said somehow this is emphasizing the bone issue that it
means the ribs and the ribcage and the and the spinal cord.
Okay so and it's also unclear is he disagreeing vertebrae or
the also?
No well the severing of the spinal cord. So right we'll see
actually later today about the vertebrae without it severing the spinal cord
but anyway that's what רש"י Rashi says. But does so and so
that's one question. Does he mean organs or does he mean bones?
And the other question is is he saying in addition to what
was said or or instead of what was said? Anyway so we
don't know exactly. אמר ליה הונא מר בריה דרב נחמיה לרב אשי.
Amar leh Huna Mar brei deRav Nechemiah leRav Ashi. So the question
was raised to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, סימנים מאי? simanim mai? What
about the trachea and the esophagus? Do you have to see whether
those have been severed or you know been נעקר? ne'ekar? אמר ליה.
Amar leh. He said to him סימנים קשים הם אצל נפילה. simanim
kashim heim eitzel nefilah.
No, when the animal falls down they are hard, they are resistant,
meaning that's not what's going to happen. That's not a problem that's
going to occur as a result of falling down. The bones might
break, the organs might sever, internal organs might get a hole, but
it's not going to affect the things going in the neck. Okay,
so that those you don't have to check.
Not right away.
It would take, take, take a couple of days till it affects
the body.
Oh that's interesting. But here we're talking about like an immediate tear.
Yeah. That, that could happen in a fall.
Yeah, when you fall down you don't feel it right away.
You don't feel it, but then if you cut open the animal,
you שחט shacht the animal, cut it open.
Yeah, if you שחט shacht the animal you cut open right away
it's not really.
I mean if we're, we're concerned here about the what? But a
tear will happen. What are you afraid of? I mean what do
you think can happen after a few days that won't happen right
away?
Well usually, usually you don't feel it right away when you're hurt.
Yeah but I'm not talking about whether the animal feels, I'm talking
about whether the injury actually occurs that you'll see by שחט shachting
the animal and opening it up.
Well it would change right away or it,
it takes a couple of days. Yeah well if it's a tear,
if it's we're afraid about broken bones or holes in organs, if
that happens as a result of the fall that will happen right
away. Yeah.
Yeah. They say uses the word קשים הם אצל נפילה. kashim heim
eitzel nefilah. The reason the bones break is because they're hard, hard.
Yeah I realize that. That's why I translated קשין kashin as resistant.
Okay so גמרא Gemara says אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel.
So that's about about like large animals and even if they get
out of this ריסוק איברים risuk eivarim you need to do internal
checks unless it walks around. So now we're saying now we're going
to move to birds which is actually a later משנה. mishna. עוף
שנחבט על פני המים. of shenichbat al pnei hamayim.
If a bird was like cast against the water, I'm not sure
exactly what happened. It fell out of its nest somehow it was
not a soft landing, it slammed against the water. Okay so you're
afraid also there about the impact. So how do you get something
parallel to standing up and walking? Birds don't birds don't walk. Well,
chickens do. Right. I guess whatever, but anyway, it's in water. Okay,
so כיון ששט מלא קומתו דיו. Keivan she'shat melo komato dayo.
As long as it swims its length, the length of its body,
then that's like it got up and walked around. And then you
don't have to worry about נפולה nefulah or ריסוק איברים. risuk evarim.
But you couldn't like, you could do the walking test if it's
on the ground.
Yeah, presumably. But here, here you didn't have that opportunity. So ולא
אמרין אלא ממטה למעלה, V'lo amrin ela mi-mata l'ma'ala, that's only if
it's going from below to above against the current. Against the current.
Thank you. Exactly. אבל ממעלה למטה, Aval mi-ma'ala l'mata, if it's going
with the current, מיהו דאצפילו, maihu d'atzpilu, it's the water moving it
down and its movement proves nothing. It can go with water. ואי
מיא קיימי לית לן בה, Ve-ee maya kaimi layt lan bah, and
if it is standing water,
I mean obviously because then there's no with or against the current.
ואי שד ציבי וקדמי, Ve-ee shat tzeevi ve-kadmei,
let's say there are little pieces of wood in the water going
with the current and this is going faster than the pieces of
wood. So it's going with the current but it's actually moving as
well. And you can see that because you see it's going faster
than the other things that are in the water that are moving
with the current. Then הקדמי, hakadmei, then fine, then it's moving, then
it's going ahead of those little things in the water and therefore
it's like walking around. Okay, now we're going to get to what
types of impacts are considered hard impacts and which are considered soft
impacts to be a problem.
So soft impact you don't have to worry at all?
Right. I mean that's right. You could imagine I guess a middle
position where you have to do a בדיקה bedika but you don't
have to worry for ריסוק איברים, risuk evarim, but the גמרא Gemara
is going to sound like it's one or the other. Let's take
a look. So we're going to start with birds. קלינא מטיח חיישינן,
Kleena mattiach khaishinan, if you have a cloak that is spread taut
and the bird fell and you know made an impact against the
cloak or maybe it did it like, this is a better way
to imagine where the energy is coming from. The cloak is spread
like perpendicular to the ground and you know you're hanging out your
laundry or something and the bird smashes into it. So that's considered
a hard impact, so that's חיישינן, khaishinan, that is a concern for
this ריסוק איברים. risuk evarim.
Wait so even if it doesn't hit the ground you're saying?
Right. It's hitting something else, before we mentioned the issue about hitting
a wall, so hitting this also is a problem. Okay, חיישינן. khaishinan.
דלא
מטיח לא חיישינן, D'lo mattiach lo khaishinan, if it's not taut, it's
not a problem. Even if it sort of stopped the bird, it
was not a harsh impact. עופא ואפא ומעופפא, Oaf for af u-m'oafef,
if it is a folded over sheet, it's a double folded sheet,
so even if it's taut, it's not going to be that taut.
If it's a folded sheet, לא חיישינן lo khaishinan and we're not
concerned. איזלא ומרכבי קטרי חיישינן, Izla u-merkavi kitrei khaishinan,
if it's a net with that's tightly knotted, the knots are close
to one another. So again you imagine I guess a horizontal net
that you're going to דווקא davka catch birds and it smashes into
the net. So if the knots are close, that makes it very
tight and it might have hit against the knot, and that's a
concern. לא מקרבי קטרי לא חיישינן, Lo mikarvi kitrei lo khaishinan, if
the knots aren't close, לא חיישינן lo khaishinan then we're not concerned.
You caught your bird, but it did not make a hard impact.
כתנא דעביד בתוני חיישינן, Kitna d'avid bituni khaishinan,
if you have flax that is in bundles, then it sort of
now maybe it fell against the ground or I don't know maybe
you have a wall of it, anyway, then it is a problem.
It's a hard impact.
דהאי גיסא ודהאי גיסא, De'hai gisa v'de'hai gisa, if it fell on
either side of the bundle like at the edges of the bundle,
I guess where it's softer, לא חיישינן lo khaishinan we're not concerned.
אסורייתא חיישינן, Assureisa khaishinan, if you have a what's a אסורייתא assureisa
again, bundle of wood, is so similarly that is a concern. אסורייתא
חיישינן. Assureisa khaishinan. כתנא דדייש ונפיץ לא חיישינן, Kitna d'daish v'naphitz lo
khaishinan,
if you have flax that is now maybe this is not a
bundle of flax now, this is flax that's being processed, a pile
of flax. So if it has been beaten and combed, so all
of the seeds have been removed from it, so then what's left
is very soft. We're not concerned. לא חיישינן. lo khaishinan. דייש ולא
נפיץ, Daish v'lo naphitz, if it's beaten but not combed, so it
still has all the hard seeds mixed up in it, so then
it still is hard and חיישינן khaishinan if it's smashed into it
we're concerned. Aren't flax like really really small?
I mean there are a lot of them.
I have no idea what a flax looks like. I'm sure Dovid
can get us from Wikipedia or something. I have no idea what
these bundles of flax look like. All
right, anyway, okay now דעביד בזרי, d'avid bizri, כיון דאיכא בה קטרי
חיישינן. keivan d'ika beh kitrei khaishinan.
Now if it is made somehow in like bundles of flax, yeah
the flax, although we actually just discussed the bundles before, but since
there are knots there that are sort of bundling it together, then
we are concerned and it because it hits into the knots and
the knots create the impact.
Wait so oh maybe you tied your flax together with knots instead
of the flax... Oh that could be. That could be.
Yeah.
How does he translate this here דעביד בזרי? d'avid bizri? Let me
take a look.
Oh I'm sorry. I'm sorry. No, בזרי bizri here it says that
they have the seed vessels are still in them.
Okay.
Good explanation here of the process. Yeah.
Softens away.
Okay, drops away.
Drops away. And you're left with
I guess the fibers that you use for whatever you use them
for. Okay. And since they are being soaked, then they're softer.
Okay. So which stage is that, the soaked? דייק ונופץ Daik ve-Nofitz
is that they're soaked and the layers were removed?
דייק ונופץ. Daik ve-Nofitz.
And דייק ולא נופץ Daik ve-lo Nofitz is that they're soaked but
the layers weren't removed?
Presumably, דייק ולא
נופץ,
Daik
ve-lo Nofitz, yeah.
Okay. So that, okay, so it's not the beating the seeds out,
it's removing this layer. And what does he say דעביד ביזרי De-avid
Bizri means?
עשוי אגודות. Asuy Agudot.
No, so that is, that is with bundles. Okay, fine. All right,
so it's similar to what I thought except that it's not removing
the seeds, it's removing this hard harder outer layer. Okay. דקשא וחשנין.
Daksha ve-Chashinan.
Now,
if you have you have, you know, these like, right, these harder
shells that were removed, so
and it hit into these outer shells. So if it was, so
what's that they were removed, so what's the story there? So that
is a problem because they're the harder shells and that's exactly, that's
exactly, you know, what made the flax better was the removing of
these shells.
Wasn't that kind of obvious?
Well, maybe, I don't know, but maybe it was the combination of
the two. דק דק סא, Dak dak-sa, if however those shells themselves
were like made were crushed finely,
לא חשנין Lo chashinan it's not a problem. It is so bizarre
these range of things that the גמרא Gemara chooses to talk about.
Could talk about any material under the sky. You imagine that maybe
this happened, maybe birds, you know, hit into these things, you know,
birds fly around and you had piles of things. I don't know.
It's bizarre which things it's deciding to discuss. נברא חשנין. Nivra chashinan.
Now, if it, if it hits into נברא Nivra which was a
type of
a thing that what do you call that, a vine, not a
vine, but anyway, some type of a thing that went around palm
trees that they took and they processed and they made it into
like hemp or string. Okay, so before when it was in the...
What?
Sounds like a vine.
Yeah, sounds like a vine. Anyway, in the original state then it's
a problem because it's still hard.
Well, if it's in the original state, then it's smacking into a
tree.
No, but it's removed from the tree but it hasn't been processed.
Oh, so you think it's put it on the ground and then...
Yeah, exactly, but it's but it's still hard. Okay. תמחסה Timchasa if
it's been processed and now it's sort of ready to be hemp
or whatever, then it's soft, לא חשנין Lo chashinan we're not afraid.
קטמא נהילה חשנין, Kitma nehila chashinan, sift
sifted ashes. So, I don't know why you're sifting ashes, if I
understood again
correctly. Let me see how they translate this. Yeah, sifted ashes, basically
essentially. Anyway, so then so therefore, where are we? קטמא נהילה חשנין
Kitma nehila chashinan is a problem because after the sifting process the
pile that results, I don't know why you're sifting your ashes, anyway,
is compressed. So therefore it's hard.
I mean but ashes are very like fine.
I know. So if they just fall naturally there's a lot of
air and it's soft. But somehow you're sifting it and you're making
some pile of compressed ashes for whatever reason, you're gathering them and
sifting them, then it's tightly packed. I don't know. חשנין. Chashinan. לא
נהילה לא חשנין Lo nehila lo chashinan not sifted not afraid. Again,
it's great, but you know these are גמרות Gemarot that I imagine
like historians love because they can try to get a sense of
what the real reality was. Who's talks about sifted ashes, who talks
about birds hitting these things? You know, so it's a certain insight
into the, you know, the details of their world. I don't know
what it looked like.
Ash is like very soft and fluffy.
Yeah, but let's say you compressed them.
It doesn't say compressed, it said you just sifted them.
Yeah, but maybe the process of sifting it can make it... It
can get...
It can get dense. Yeah. Okay. Put water on.
Okay. Top of נב עמוד א. Nun-Bet Amud Aleph. Okay. חול הדק
לא חשנין, Chol ha-dak lo chashinan, fine sand isn't a problem. Again,
you would think that fine sand would be compressed and would be
a problem. I don't know. Anyway, חול הגס, Chol ha-gas, thick sand
which also is more like, you know, pebbly and larger clumps and
more afraid it hits into them, that is a problem. Again, it's
here which seems like it's smashing into the ground not into a
wall of this stuff. אבק דרכים חשנין, Avak drachim chashinan, normal dust
from the on the dirt on the way is a problem. Because
why? Is it hitting the actual, you know, dirt path itself? That
makes sense. If it's just collecting dust, I don't know, a little
doesn't makes little less sense. But anyway, but רשי Rashi says it
we are talking somehow that it is gathered together and compressed.
Which people walk on it all day.
I guess, yeah, then it's just hitting the dirt path. תיבנא ועביד
בזיגא חשנין. Tibna ve-avid be-ziga chashinan. If you have straw made again
into bundles, that is a problem because it's tight. לא עביד בזיגא
Lo avid be-ziga just straw lying there on a pile but not
in a bundle, לא חשנין Lo chashinan is not a problem. חטי
וכל דמיניהו, Chiti ve-chol de-minayhu, wheat and all things like wheat, which
רשי Rashi basically says means all other types of like harder grains,
that is a problem. שערי Se'arei barley, וכל דמיניהו ve-chol de-minayhu and
everything like it, and here the risk here if you look at
the side is לא חשנין Lo chashinan because we actually have been
dealing with... pairs, חיישינן, chashinan, לא חיישינן, lo chashinan, so this makes
sense, this לא חיישינן, lo chashinan, otherwise it would have just combined
them. So apparently barley is a softer grain for impact than things
like wheat, basically. כל מיני קטניות אין בהם ריסוק אברים. kol minei
kitniyos ein bahem risuk evarim. All types of lentils don't have ריסוק
אברים. risuk evarim. Very interesting, the whole shift of tone. Not חיישינן
chashinan or לא חיישינן, lo chashinan, but אין בהם ריסוק אברים. ein
bahem risuk evarim. רש״י Rashi says because the issue about the קטניות
kitniyos is not so much that they're soft, but this is what
the גמרא Gemara is going to say, that if you try to
stack them, they don't really even like stack together. They all sort
of fly off of one another. So it's almost not like it's
an impact but on a soft thing, it's almost like there's no
impact, right? The stuff doesn't even really stay together. Okay.
Now,
לבר levar with the exception מן רוביא רוביא min rubaya rubaya with
the exception of רוביא rubaya which רש״י Rashi says תלתן taltan which
if I remember correctly is... Taltan's what? תלתן taltan which if I
remember correctly is fenugreek, which now that explains a lot. Apparently that
can stack well and compress well. Let me take a look here.
I think I have to look all these things up. Let's see
what it says.
It is called fenugreek.
Once again,
fenugreek.
That helps. Now we know exactly what we're talking about.
Okay, and that's חמצי. chamtzei.
Exactly. Anyway, okay. לבר... levar... חמצי אין בו משום ריסוק אברים. chamtzei
ein bo mishum risuk evarim. חמצי chamtzei is again some other type
of a of a of a lentil type of a thing that
רש״י Rashi says also slides and does not stack, so that's not
a problem.
But חפצי chaptzei is not a קטניות kitniyot then?
Yeah, so תוספות Tosafot discusses like it's not a classic קטניות kitniyot
or whatever. חפצי chaptzei which is another type of a thing which
which is not circular and does stack, יש בו משום ריסוק אברים
yesh bo mishum risuk evarim is a problem of ריסוק אברים. risuk
evarim.
What does it say? The first one is what?
חפצי chaptzei is chickpeas according to Artscroll.
And חמצי, chamtzei,
the first one?
Oh, just peas. Oh, and those are קטניות? kitniyot?
Well,
let's not make גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. Okay, anyway, so it says
peas is not a problem because they slide, although I guess peas
and pea are in a pod. But right, anyway, and chickpeas, how
do chickpeas come naturally? Chickpeas?
Chickpeas...
they're large beans. Yeah, but do they come in a pod?
So I don't know, I don't know why that would more have
משום ריסוק אברים. mishum risuk evarim.
Look what fenugreek seeds look like.
Oh, okay. I've never seen fenugreek before. What does it say?
Okay, so anyway, I'm not exactly sure he has... yeah.
Chickpeas is not a problem but lentils is a problem. So it
says chickpeas is the first one, it's not a problem. Lentils is
no. Okay, moving on. All right. כללא דמילתא, klala demilta, the general
rule is, thank you. כל מידי דמישרק אין בו משום ריסוק אברים,
kol midi demishrak ein bo mishum risuk evarim, anything that slips, that
does not sort of stick together is not a problem because it
doesn't make much of an impact. אין בו משום... ein bo mishum...
ריסוק אברים. risuk evarim.
דלא מישרק, dela mishrak, I guess if it doesn't slip, then יש
בו משום ריסוק אברים yesh bo mishum risuk evarim there is a
concern. דבוק. davuk. Now how about something רש״י Rashi basically says, if
you look at רש״י Rashi under דבוק, davuk, רש״י Rashi says לודא,
luda, glue. Okay, so apparently this would be like a type of
a bird trap that they would glue some types of pieces of
wood and the bird would land on it. And then when it
would try to fly away, it would stick to the pieces of
wood and it would fall to the ground. Okay, one wonders why
they didn't just... why they made it loose pieces of wood, why
not just have it... but maybe it wouldn't have landed on it.
I don't know. Anyway, so now it's got this piece of wood
stuck to it or stuck to a wing or something like that
and because of that it falls to the ground. So is that
considered ריסוק אברים? risuk evarim? Now we're not concerned what is it
hitting into, but is the fact that it is crashing into the
ground because its wings are stuck to something create a experience of
falling and crashing to be ריסוק אברים? risuk evarim? So let's take
a look. רב אשי שרי, Rav Ashi shari, Rav Ashi says no
problem. רב אמימר אסר, Rav Amimar assar, Rav Amimar says no good.
בחד גפא דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דשרי. bechad gapa dechulei alma la
peligi deshari. If it's only stuck, immobilized one wing, then everybody agrees
and nevertheless it falls, then it's permissible. That that's not going to
be a harsh landing. כי פליגי בתרי גפי, ki peligi betrei gapei,
the issue is when both wings are immobilized. מאן דאסר אמר לך,
man deassar amar lach, the one who forbids says to you, היכי
ניקום, heichi neikum, how is it supposed to get up? Since it
cannot, you know, move and fly and whatever, if it's going to
fall and both wings are immobilized, it's going to be a serious
impact.
But how's it supposed to get up though?
No, it it landed on some branch with this trap and then
it fell off the branch but couldn't fly away so it
hit the ground.
Yes. Okay. ומאן דשרי אמר לך, uman deshari amar lach, the one
who says it's permissible will say to you, אפשר דניקום אעקבי דגפי.
efshar denikum a'ikvei degapei. No, it could somehow still support itself by
the... by literally the heel of the wing, which I would have
thought it meant the tip of the wing, but רש״י Rashi makes
it sound a little bit like it means the top of the
wing where it's combined to the body. I'm not sure. Anyway, but
anyway, somehow there's a part of the wing that is still mobile,
so that helps it break its fall. So it's not going to
be... it's not... So it's not going to be completely like
a strong of an impact as is necessary to create a problem.
Okay, so that's one explanation.
Okay, איכא דאמרי Ika Damri and others say
בתרי גפי כולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסור. Betrei Gapei Kulei Alma Lo
Pligi Deasur. No, both wings everybody is going to agree it can't
fly, any fall is going to be pretty strong impact. כי פליגי
בחד גפא, Ki Pligi Bechad Gapa, they disagree when it's one wing
that's immobilized. מאן דשרי אמר לך אפשר דפרח בחד גפא, Man Desharei
Amar Lach Efshar Deparch Bechad Gapa, the one that permits says look
it can still fly with one wing, flap with one wing, so
even though it's not going to really fly fly well but that
will prevent a strong crash into the ground. ומאן דאסר, Uman Deasur,
the one who forbids will say כיון דבהאי לא מציה פרחה בהאי
נמי לא מציה פרחה. Keivan Debehai Lo Matzya Parchah Behai Nami Lo
Matzya Parchah. Since it can't fly with one, it can't fly with
the other. So it can't really do anything with one wing that
does not give it any control, any support, and it will be
a strong fall. I mean sometimes you see this right that birds
have an injured wing and they it's you know and is the
wing doing anything for the remaining wing? Is that doing anything for
them? I don't think so. If it fell from a branch with
one injured wing would the flapping of the other wing be completely
ineffectual or would it do something to cushion the fall?
It might cushion it but it's not
going to be able to it's not going to be able to
fly right. Okay, so anyway that's I think a little more interesting
debate that it's just one wing will that do enough to cushion
the fall. והלכתא Vehilchata the halakha is we split our vote. בתרי
גפי אסור Betrei Gapei Asur if both wings are immobilized that is
a problem. בחד גפא שרי Bechad Gapa Sharei one wing we say
the fall will not be with enough of an impact to create
a problem. So interestingly in this Gemara we introduce the bird discussion
although that's a later...
we don't mention a בהמה.
Behema. We don't mention right some of these things for בהמה Behema
right? And we also you know also implicitly or explicitly whatever you
know imported the whole idea from the bird discussion about standing up
and walking around etc. that that solves the immediate problem but in
some cases you still have to check for internal injuries. Okay, so
that is this weird category of פירוק עצמות Piruk Atzamot or ריסוק
איברים Risuk Evarim which is not a particular inner injury but just
a the fall itself if it does not stand up afterwards. And
now we get back to the and now we're back to the
Mishnah. The next line in the Mishnah is about an injury but
more of a but it's moving away again from the internal organs
and it speaks about the breaking of bones. And here we get
to רוב צלעותיה Rov Tzaloteha a majority of its ribs. Now apparently
a animal, a cow at least has you know it's got the
ribcage ribs the ones that go all the way around the front.
In this picture you sort of see that they draw them a
little bit longer. These are the ones that go all the way
down. Okay, and then the ones towards the back of the spine
are a little go a little bit but they don't really you
know they're not ribcage. What? Do we have those types of ribs
too?
One floating rib. Only one.
Okay, but the animals apparently have like a lot of ribs over
here that are ribcage ribs and then small ones and apparently at
least the way the Gemara describes it these ones in the back
that are not part of the ribcage don't have marrow in them.
אין בהם מוח. Ein Bahem Moach. So that's the way the Gemara
distinguishes. So when we speak about breaking the ribs we mean the
ribs of the ribcage. Apparently also there are a there are
eleven ribs. So it is a is eleven? Hold on one minute.
No, I'm sorry eleven on each side. There's eleven ribs on each
side.
Okay, there's thirteen.
Thirteen? That's not what רש״י Rashi says.
רש״י Rashi says that there are eleven on each side for total
of twenty-two.
Oh yeah, actually they quote רש״י Rashi saying eleven but it says
actually cows, sheep and goats have thirteen pairs of ribs.
Thirteen pairs. Twenty-six. Okay, okay the problem is that the Gemara is
going to assume that the majority of the ribs the Gemara is
going to assume is going to be twelve. So רש״י Rashi is
just reflecting the Gemara. So it's very interesting. Unless Gemara the only
way to reconcile that is to say there might be thirteen pairs
but only eleven pairs matter. You know for whatever reason the
Gemara says only eleven have marrow.
Have marrow. Ah, so when the Gemara is excluding the non-marrow it's
not just excluding the back ones it's excluding even the last two
of the ribcage that are presumably without marrow. Okay fine. So there
there might be thirteen pairs of actual rib ribs of the ribcage
but there are only eleven with marrow, the top eleven, and those
are the ones we care about.
And the more after
the ribcage that don't have marrow at all. And the ones that
don't have marrow or that are not part of the ribcage don't
matter.
You trying to say thirteen in the ribcage or thirteen overall? No,
thirteen overall.
Oh overall. Oh so then it's no problem at all because רש״י
Rashi also is only talking about the ones that are part of
the ribcage. All right, we'll have to check our anatomical charts later.
But anyway there are the ones that are part of the ribcage
that have the marrow that matter for our discussion are eleven pair
okay? And then there are some small ribs below that that are
either not part of the ribcage and or don't have marrow. So
let's take a look. Now if we need the majority of ribs
so if you have eleven pairs the majority of that is how
many ribs? Everybody do your math. Six. Twelve right? Eleven pairs so
half of that is eleven because eleven pairs twenty-two. So the majority
of eleven pairs... is 12 ribs. So let's take a look. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. אלו הן
רוב צלעות. Eilu hein rov tzalot. These are the ways you get
the majority of the ribs, שש מכאן ושש מכאן. Sheish mikan v'sheish
mikan. Either you can get six on each side, okay, or אחת
עשרה מכאן ואחת מכאן, achas esrei mikan v'achas mikan, or you get
all 11 on one side and one on the other, and obviously
implicitly is in any combination in between. Meaning as long as 11
ribs are being broken from these... 12 ribs are being broken from
these 11 pairs, it doesn't matter if they are primarily all on
one side, they're equally divided, as long as the majority of ribs
are being broken. So 12 ribs is the majority, however it's divided.
אמר זעירי. Amar Zeiri.
Would they be like completely broken, through and through?
Ah, ואמר זעירי, V'amar Zeiri, מחציין כלפי שדרה. mechetzayan klapei shidra. Only
when they are broken from the half of the rib towards the
rib cage. You know, if you imagine like here's the spinal cord
and here are the ribs, so it is the top half of
the rib that is closest to the spinal cord. Right? So that's
where it's obviously more critical. When it's the bottom half of the
rib, away from the spinal cord, it is not considered a full
break. Okay, so אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbah Bar Bar Chana Amar Rabbi Yochanan, ובצלעות גדולות שיש בהן מוח.
u-vitzalot gedolot she-yeish bahen moach. And here we clarify, we're talking about
the large ribs, the one of the rib cage, not what James
says is called the floaters. The large ribs that actually have the
marrow, and those are 11 on each side. Okay, אמר עולא. Amar
Ulla. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, says we have a picture.
Okay, bring it in.
Okay, yeah, well we sort of configured that. Okay, thanks.
It's a booby trap. Exactly.
Okay. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, so עולא Ulla says, where are we?
אמר עולא בן זכאי אומר. Amar Ulla Ben Zakkai omer. So interesting,
בן זכאי Ben Zakkai says.
Wasn't that רבי יוחנן בן זכאי? Rabbi Yochanan Ben Zakkai?
Yeah, what generation is עולא? Ulla? Does anybody know? I'm not good
at that generations of the
אמוראי. Amorai. Hard to imagine that's רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan
Ben Zakkai because בן זכאי Ben Zakkai was at the very beginning
of, but he's also the very beginning of the תנאי Tannai period.
Yeah, no, yeah, yeah,
yeah. Couldn't be. Some other בן זכאי. Ben Zakkai. His younger brother.
בן זכאי אומר,
Ben Zakkai omer, נעקרו ברוב צד אחד. ne'ekru b'rov tzad echad. When,
now we've been talking about broken ribs. Let's say the rib isn't
broken, let's say it actually is uprooted from its combination, like ripped
out of where it's combined to the spinal cord. So there he's
going to say that's even... that's... that's worse. So נעקרו ברוב צד
אחד. ne'ekru b'rov tzad echad. If they were actually uprooted, then as
long as it's the majority of one side, then as long as
it's six ribs from one side, or maybe a total of six.
נשתברו, nishtabru, if they're broken, what we've been talking about, then ברוב
שני צדדין. b'rov shenei tzdadin. Then you need the majority of both
sides combined, then you need 12 ribs. Okay. רבי יוחנן אומר, Rabbi
Yochanan omer, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, בין נעקרו בין נשתברו,
bein ne'ekru bein nishtabru, whether they have been uprooted or whether they've
just been broken, ברוב שני צדדין, b'rov shenei tzdadin, you need the
majority of both sides, you need 12 ribs. אמר
רב, Amar Rav, so רב Rav says, נעקרה צלע וחוליה עמה. ne'ekra
tzela v'chulya imah. Now you've been talking about it was just uprooted
from where it combined to the spinal cord. Let's say a rib
combined with its
חוליה. chulya. The vertebrae, thanks. Combined with the vertebrae, if completely removed.
So it's not just removed from where it combined to the vertebrae,
but it is removed from the spinal cord with the vertebrae. That
he says, that would be more drastic, and
ואפילו אחת טריפה. v'afilu achat tereifah. Even one rib if it's removed
with its vertebrae is a טריפה. tereifah. So אמר ליה רב כהנא
ורב אסי לרב, Amarei leih Rav Kahana v'Rav Assi l'Rav, so they
said to רב, Rav, נעקרה צלע מכאן וצלע מכאן וחוליה קיימת מהו.
ne'ekra tzela mikan v'tzela mikan v'chulya kayemes mahu. So you said a
whole rib with its vertebrae. Let's say you have the ribs on
each side removed, but the vertebrae in the middle, meaning one pair
of ribs is fully removed but the... but the vertebrae in the
middle is still there, what's the story there? So it's interesting that
they imagine that it's worse when it's on... when it's an entire
unit, right, on both sides, when it's a pair. Okay, so what
is the story there?
So you have them uprooted, is that like...
Yeah, pulled out of where it's...
like pulled out of where
it's combined, like at the joint, exactly. Okay.
So רב Rav said when he removed it with the vertebrae. They
said what if you have it on both sides of the vertebrae
but the vertebrae is there, what would that be the story? אמר
להו, Amar lehu, so he said back to them, גיסטרא קא רמיתו?
gistera ka ramitu? What, you're talking about a גיסטרא? gistera? Now you
remember גיסטרא gistera was the animal that you chopped in half. When
you basically chop an animal in half width-wise, even though it was
still alive, it was considered already a נבילה. neveilah. Meaning even though
it was breathing or whatever, it was considered a נבילה neveilah once
you basically chopped it in half width-wise. So he assumes, very interestingly,
I would say bizarrely, that if you've removed a rib on each
side, it's essentially like slicing the animal in half, which is a
pretty big jump. Now what he's basically saying is a rib on
each side, that's like cutting it in half, and therefore forget about
being a טריפה, tereifah, it's even a נבילה. neveilah. Okay, once this
has occurred, which is, again, pretty shocking that just missing a rib
on each side of the spinal cord we would consider it, A,
even that we'd consider it a טריפה tereifah and that he thinks
it's for granted that it's worse, that it's a נבילה. neveilah. Okay,
but that's what he said. So now we're going to have to
see how this factors in as being obviously worse than the other
cases we've been talking about. So let's take a look.
But it was, let's say, born without one rib or something. And
would that matter?
That's an interesting question. I don't know. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says והא רב נמי גיסטרא קאמר. Veha Rav nami gistera ka'amar. How
is this different than רב? Rav? רב Rav spoke about it also
being uprooted with its with its what do you call it חוליה.
chulya. Now I should say more than that, it's not just that
with its חוליה chulya is logically as bad as on both sides.
But what happens if you remove a rib with its vertebrae? What
happens to the rib on the other side? Right? It doesn't just
float in midair, it also falls out. So רב's Rav's case of
a rib with its vertebrae includes their case. They were actually saying
something that was less severe than רב. Rav. You said a rib
and its vertebrae, which obviously also means the other rib, and that
that's a טריפה. treifa. We want to know if it's the two
ribs and not the vertebrae. Oh that's totally a גיסטרא, gistera, that's
a נבילה. neveila. So that's your case. Your case is even worse
than that. It's one rib with the vertebrae, which means the other
rib won't be there either. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara
answers. So the גמרא Gemara says כי קאמר רב צילא בלא חוליה.
Ki ka'amar Rav tzela belo chulya. No רב Rav said a rib
without the vertebrae. So the גמרא Gemara says what do you mean?
וצילא וחוליה קאמר. Vetzela vechulya ka'amar. He said explicitly the rib and
the vertebrae. So that's also then of course with the other ribs.
So what's going on? So the גמרא Gemara says no, here's what
he means. צילא וחצי חוליה. Tzela vachatzi chulya. רב Rav did not
literally mean the rib and the entire vertebrae because that would take
the other rib with it. He meant the rib and half the
vertebrae where it's connected to. The other half where the other rib
is connected to still remains. So that was רב's Rav's case. And
then רב Rav assumed that their case about two ribs, one from
each side, was obviously worse than his case of one rib with
half of a vertebrae, which is interesting. מכלל Michlal the גמרא Gemara
says רב כהנא ורב אסי צילא בלא חוליה אמרי. Rav Kahana veRav
Assi tzela belo chulya amri. So רב כהנא ורב אסי Rav Kahana
veRav Assi therefore were asking him if it's a rib on each
side, you said a rib with half a vertebrae which allowed the
other rib to remain. What if you have both ribs, parallel ribs
removed, but no vertebrae? Okay
and ואמר להו גיסטרא קאמריתו. Ve'amar lehu gistera ka'amritu. And he said
back to them, oh what are you talking about? That's clearly a
problem. That's like a נבילה neveila again. It's a little surprising that
that's so obviously a problem, but nevertheless at least it's clear how
he made their case worse than his case. His case was with
half a vertebrae, their case was no vertebrae but both ribs. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, how could he say that that's
a נבילה? neveila? והאמר עולא דן בן זכאי אמר נעקרו ברוב צד
אחד נשתברו ברוב שני צדדים. Veha'amar Ulla dan Ben Zakkai amar ne'ekru
berov tzad echad nishtabru berov shenei tzedadim. So how does what
does בן זכאי Ben Zakkai say? That when it comes to נעקרו,
ne'ekru, when you have which is their case נעקרו, ne'ekru, it's uprooted,
it's a problem as long as it's a majority. So we're assuming
if it's a majority of one side, six, that would even allow
for the case of two ribs, parallel ribs. So how come he's
saying that he's saying that you need רוב, rov, and you're saying
just two ribs create a problem. So here the answer's easy. Here
the answer is, where were we? אמר
לך התם זה שלא כנגד זה. Amar lach hatam zeh shelo keneged
zeh. When בן זכאי Ben Zakkai said נעקרו ne'ekru you needed a
majority, that was when they were not parallel, when they were not
from the same line. הכא זה כנגד זה. Hacha zeh keneged zeh.
Their question was when it was parallel. So what have we tried
to do now to make all these pieces fit together? Okay, we
said broken ribs you need 12. Uprooted ribs you need six. But
that's when they're not on the same line. רב Rav says if
it's uprooted with half of a vertebrae
that's a טריפה. treifa. Up until now we weren't talking with a
vertebrae. רב כהנא ורב אסי Rav Kahana veRav Assi were asking about
two parallel ribs uprooted without the vertebrae. And there רב Rav said,
oh my God that's even worse, that's a גיסטרא. gistera. Why is
it worse than just stam uprooted ribs? Because here they're parallel and
up until now we'd been talking about non-parallel. But now the גמרא's
Gemara's going to say one minute, I'm going to prove to you
we were even talking about parallel until now. Let's take a look.
Parallel really is not the right word because actually the ribs on
one side are parallel, really the line is like in the same
line but okay. What? Opposite. Opposite, thank you.
Opposing ribs. Okay anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
one minute, והאמר רבי יוחנן Veha'amar Rabbi Yochanan one minute, but רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said
ברוב שני צדדים. Berov shenei tzedadim. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says even
when the ribs are uprooted you need the majority of both sides
combined, which is 12. Now, if you're going to get 12 and
each side only has 11, at least one at least in one
place you're going to have opposing ribs, right? If you did six
and six you'd have six sets of opposing ribs. But even if
you did 11 and one you're going to have one pair of
opposing ribs. And even so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says you needed
the majority. Just two opposing ribs are not going to be enough
by themselves. So ברוב שני צדדים וברוב שני צדדים. Berov shenei tzedadim
uverov shenei tzedadim. When you do the majority of both sides, 12,
אי אפשר דלא קאי חדא
מינייהו זה כנגד זה. Ee efshar delo ka'ei chada mineihu zeh keneged
zeh. You're never, you'll have at least one pair of opposing ribs.
So if you say one pair of opposing ribs is already גיסטרא,
gistera, which is a נבילה, neveila, how could רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
say you need a majority just to get it to be a
טריפה? treifa? So the גמרא Gemara says, okay we're trying to make
everything work so anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: התם בוכנא בלא אסיטא הכא בוכנא ואסיטא. Hatam buchna belo
asita hacha buchna ve'asita. Ball and
socket. Exactly. So the בוכנא buchna is the ball and the אסיתא
asita is the socket. So essentially it's talking once again about the
what do you call it, about the vertebrae. So it says when
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan says if it's uprooting you need 12 and
opposing would not be a problem in itself, that's when it's just
uprooted with no part of the actual socket. When they when רב
Rav said opposing would be a גיסטרא, gistra, that's בוכנא ואסיתא. buchna
va'asita. That would be the ball with part of the socket.
But not the vertebrae.
But but now we're back but the socket is the vertebrae. So
now we've come full circle. So רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan says fine
you need a majority blah blah that's uprooted. They רב Rav says
that their saying was a גיסטרא gistra when it was with the
socket. But if it's with the socket, then רב Rav himself says
that that it's just one rib with part of the socket. So
why are they asking two ribs with part of the socket? And
why does רב Rav treat that as being so much radically well
why it's worse we can accept. He was talking one rib part
of the socket, they're talking about opposing rib part of the socket.
But why did they ask it given that רב Rav had already
ruled about one rib and part of the socket? So let's take
a look. אי הכי היינו דרב, ei hachi hainu derav, that's already
implicit in רב's Rav ruling about one rib. לא שמיע להו דרב.
lo shemia lehu derav. They didn't hear רב's Rav ruling. They just
סתם stam asked רב Rav a question. It's true, רב Rav had
already said one one rib and a socket and they didn't hear
and they asked him two ribs and a socket. Now again you
have to realize this is completely again against how it sounded from
the beginning. From the beginning it's like this: רב Rav said if
you remove one rib and the socket. And they say oh, but
what if it's two opposing ribs without the socket? They're exactly responding
to רב. Rav. You had told me a rib with a socket,
I want to know two opposing ribs without the socket. But because
of to make it fit with רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan and to
make it fit with how רב Rav treated it as radically different,
we've had to re-read them that they're talking also with the socket.
Well if it's with the socket, then they couldn't have heard what
רב Rav said because it was already implicit. So we have to
re-read the whole thing. Okay, so they didn't hear what רב Rav
said and they wanted to know opposing ribs with the socket. So
the גמרא Gemara said like this: וליבעי מיניה כדרב. velivai minei kederav.
If they hadn't heard what רב Rav said, why did they ask
about two ribs with the socket? Why didn't they say one rib
with the socket, which is what רב Rav was talking about? So
they didn't know what רב Rav had ruled. But if you have
a question, why don't you start by saying what's the story about
one rib and the socket? Why do you jump to the two
rib case? So סברי savri they figured, ליבעי מיניה חדא דפרש לן
תרתי. libai minei chada de-parash lan tarti.
Let's ask one question which will get two answers out of him.
Meaning, if we say two ribs and the socket and he says
it's כשרה, kesherah, it's not a טרפה, treifah, then certainly one rib
with the socket isn't a טרפה. treifah. So therefore they asked two,
they figured one answer will count for both. Of course it only
works one way. Because if he says it is a טרפה, treifah,
you still don't know the answer about one rib. So that's what
the גמרא Gemara is going to say. דאי בעי מיניה חדא, de-ei
bai minei chada, if we ask him just about one rib, הניחא
אי אמר לן טרפה, hanicha ei amar lan treifah, if he tells
us one rib with the socket is a טרפה, treifah, כל שכן
תרתי, kol sheken tarti, certainly two ribs. אי אמר לן כשרה, ei
amar lan kesherah, but if he tells us one rib with the
socket is כשרה, kesherah, אכתי תרתי קמיבעיא לן, achati tarti kamibaia lan,
we're not going to know the story about two ribs with the
socket. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, but nevertheless if you ask
two you still have the same problem. אי הכי השתא נמי דקבעי
מיניה תרתי. ei hachi hashta nami dekabaia minei tarti. Even if you're
asking him about two ribs, הניחא אי אמר להו כשרה, hanicha ei
amar lehu kesherah, if he tells you the two ribs is is
כשרה, kesherah, כל שכן חדא, kol sheken chada, then certainly one rib
with the socket is כשרה. kesherah. ואי אמר להו טרפה, ve-ei amar
lehu treifah, but if he tells you that two ribs with the
socket is a טרפה, treifah, which he did, אכתי חדא מיבעיא לן,
achati chada mibaia lan, you still don't know what the הלכה halacha
would be with one rib. So any question you ask if you
don't know the answer, you can't assume you're going to figure out
the other case. So the גמרא Gemara says no, סברי savri they
figured here's what they figured. אם כן מרתח קא רתח. im ken
mirtach ka ratach. We're going to figure out by his one answer
both things based on the tone in which he answers also. Okay,
because if we ask him two and he gets and אם כן
מרתח קא רתח, im ken mirtach ka ratach, and if he gets
angry and says, "Two? Of course two is a טרפה!" treifah! So
then we can figure out that one is also a טרפה. treifah.
So ממה נפשך, mimah nafshach, if we say two and he says
it's כשרה, kesherah, then we'll know one is כשרה. kesherah. If he
says two and he's like "Of course two is a טרפה," treifah,
then we'll know one is a טרפה. treifah. If he says two
and he says "Oh, two? That's a טרפה," treifah, then we'll know
that two's a טרפה treifah and one isn't. So we'll figure it
all out based on tone. What?
Were they short on time with the רבי? Rebbi?
That is a good question. Maybe he was short on patience.
Since they already figured that they can infer the answer based on
his tone, so they
figured they'd potentially risk angering the רבי. Rebbi.
Right, exactly.
Or they were embarrassed to ask him, right?
It sounds like or actually or maybe he was short on time
and short on patience, right? And you know and also right he
might have gotten like annoyed why you ask such a stupid question
you should know.
Especially if you're actually a תלמיד חכם.
talmid chacham. How much are you going to risk annoying your רבי
Rebbi with stupid questions? So you ask one question that at most
even if it is a stupid question you have all the answers
that you need.
Or maybe it's like today where we have עסקנים askanim surrounding all
the great גדולי ישראל gedolei Yisrael and you only get five five
seconds to ask one question and then they go the next person.
That could be.
Okay, anyway, there's no such thing as there's no such thing as
a stupid question. That doesn't apply.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
but don't we know though, I mean, because we have different opinions,
right? If it's, you know, it's not like our... Well let's finish
the answer.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: חדא טרפה תרתי מיבעיא?
Chada terefa tartei mibaya? So they'll tell me what
what type of stupid question is that? If one is a טרפה,
terefa, why are you asking about two? So if you ask two,
you'll know what the story is. If he says kosher, certainly one
is kosher. If he says oh two is טרף, teref, then you'll
say okay but one is kosher. If he says two of course
two is טרף, teref, one is טרף, teref, why are you asking?
Then we'll know that too. So the גמרא Gemara says: והא קאמרי
ליה ולא רתח? Veha ka amrei leh velo ratch? But the גמרא
Gemara says, but one minute, they asked him too and he didn't
get angry. And according to you, he should have, because רב Rav
himself paskened that even one was a problem. And we don't have
the record that he got angry. So the גמרא Gemara says: היא
דקאמרי ליה גסטרא קא משוי. Hee d'ka amri leh gistra ka misve.
Since he said to them: what are you talking about? That animal
is like a נבלה neveila already. So היינו רתיחיה. hainu rathichei. That's
his getting angry. He got annoyed. So okay, so there you go.
They asked two, from the two we inferred that one is a
problem and therefore and we also learned out that two is a
problem and even a worse problem, it's a pseudo-נבלה neveila or it
is a נבלה. neveila. Okay, you have a quick question Michael?
Yeah, yeah, I was thinking that it seems that there's still a
different opinion of נעקרה מצד אחד nekra mitzad echad versus נשברו רוב
שני צדדים. nishberu rov shnei tzdadim.
As opposed to, so according to one opinion there's still a difference
between so if it is uprooted without the vertebrae, that's the debate
we started with. Is it just like broken and you need twelve
or is it worse than broken? Right, so we still didn't answer
anyway. Right, what's debated. Okay. But with the vertebrae, that's this issue
that even one...
I understand. So are they going to answer that or we'll see...
What answer? Are they going to paskin? Yeah, how often does the
גמרא Gemara paskin?
I mean we
see it a couple of times. Here and there, usually the גמרא
Gemara paskens a lot more than it does in other places. Anyway,
let's go on. Okay. אמר רבה בר בר שילא
אמר רב מתנא
אמר שמואל:
Amar Rabba bar bar Shila amar Rav
Matna
amar Shmuel: נעקרה צלע מעיקרה וגולגולת שנחבסה ברובה ובשר חופה את רוב
הכרס ברובה טרפה. Nekra tzeila me'ikara vegulgolet shenichbesa beruba uvashar hofe et
rov hakeres beruba terefa.
Now you'll remember that this is part of the שבע שמעתתא, shev
shmaiteta, there are seven teachings of טרפות terefas that are mentioned by
אמוראים Amoraim that are not connected to the משנה. Mishnah. So this
is three of them. One is נעקרה. nekra. So the one is
what we have just been saying basically in the name of רב,
Rav, which is נעקרה צלע מעיקרה. nekra tzeila me'ikara. That it's uprooted
from where it joins, which presumably means with the, what do you
call it, with at least a portion of the vertebrae. And that's
what רב Rav taught, that just one rib by itself is a
טרפה. terefa. רש"י Rashi says here that means even without the vertebrae,
but תוספות Tosafot says but that goes against everything we've been saying
until now.
But it's still the rib
though, it can't be like a limb. Right, right. So one is
a rib without the vertebrae, that's added to the list of טרפות,
terefas, it's not in the גמרא, Gemara, but a rib, a full
rib that's uprooted with a part of the vertebrae, which is repeating
what we just said. But now we're adding two more: גולגולת שנחבסה
ברובה, Gulgoles shenichbesa beruba, a head that's been bashed in in the
majority of it, without actually cracking the skull, but just sort of
like bashing it in without actually cracking.
Like an indentation.
Yeah, I don't know, yeah, basically, right. ובשר חופה את רוב הכרס
ברובה, Uvashar hofe et rov hakeres beruba,
and this abdominal muscle which covers the majority of the כרס, keress,
if that is the majority of that is torn, then those are
a טרפה. terefa. So that's three new טרפות terefas not mentioned in
the משנה. Mishnah. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to look
at them. נעקרה צלע מעיקרה טרפה. Nekra tzeila me'ikara terefa. So that
you're saying that's טרפה, teref, which presumably is what we were talking
about until now. ורמינהי, Veramini, I'll ask on this, top of נב
עמוד ב. nun bet amud bet. כמה חסרון בשדרה? Kama chisaron bashidra?
How much if a spinal cord is lacking from its vertebrae is
the skeleton no longer considered whole, a human skeleton, and would no
longer cause טומאה tuma in an אהל? ohel? So בית שמאי אומרים
שתי חוליות, Beit Shammai omrim shtei hulyot, two vertebrae. Now we're talking
about the vertebrae, not the rib. ובית הלל אומרים חוליה אחת, Uveit
Hillel omrim hulya achat, one vertebrae. ואמר רבי יהודה אמר שמואל וכן
לטרפה, Veamar Rabbi Yehuda amar Shmuel v'chen letrefa, the same הלכה halakha
for טרפה, terefa, whatever makes it no longer full for being causing
טומאה tuma in its tent also means that an animal can't live
and it's a טרפה. terefa. So here you see that it's one
vertebrae, which is different than what you said, which is one full
rib. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, different doesn't mean contradictory. The
גמרא Gemara says: הכא צלע בלא חוליה התם חוליה בלא צלע. Hacha
tzeila belo hulya hatam hulya belo tzeila.
Here we're talking about a rib without the vertebrae, that's enough to
make it a טרפה. terefa. There we're talking about a vertebrae without
the rib. So either one. And by the way, that teaching of
a vertebrae without the rib is one of the תנאי tana'itic things
not mentioned in our משנה Mishnah that adds to the list of
טרפות. terefas. So now we've added two things to the list of
טרפות: terefas: a vertebrae without the rib and a rib without the
vertebrae. Now that's why רש"י Rashi says we mean a rib without
any part of the vertebrae. But again, that goes against everything we
said on the עמוד א. amud alef. So תוספות Tosafot says no
no no, we mean part of a vertebrae, not the full vertebrae.
Okay, so you have a rib totally uprooted with part of the
vertebrae, we'll read it like תוספות. Tosafot. That's one addition to the
list and the other is a full vertebrae. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, one minute. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: בשלמא צלע בלא חוליה משכחת לה. Bishlama tzeila belo hulya mishkachat
la.
I understand how you get a rib without totally removing the vertebrae,
of course you can do that. אלא חוליה בלא צלע היכי משכחת
לה? Ella hulya belo tzeila heichi mishkachat la? How do you remove
a vertebrae without also getting the rib? How could you say the
vertebrae by itself? Right? If you remove a vertebrae, the ribs will
come off with it. So then just say the rib, and that
implicitly includes the case of removing
the vertebrae. The floating vertebrae
you can remove a vertebra without removing a rib. So a floating
rib. Oh, okay. So whatever, but there also are places where you
have vertebrae here, right, where you don't have any ribs, right? If
you look at this picture, right, the whole bottom part of the
spinal cord. Okay, so anyway, so there we have two new additions
now to our list: majority of the ribs broken, and now we
have also uprooted just one rib with at least let's say part
of the vertebrae, and now we also have a removed vertebra even
with no ribs, the vertebrae at the bottom, or two depending on
בית הלל, Beis Hillel, בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Okay, מתקיף ליה רב
הושעיא, matkif lei Rav Oshaya, now that we've mentioned בית הלל, Beis
Hillel, בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, we have a question: ונתני גבי קולי
בית שמאי וחומרי בית הלל, venitni gabi kulei Beis Shammai vechumrei Beis
Hillel, why isn't this a leniency of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and
a stringency of בית הלל, Beis Hillel, which we normally identify those
as, why stringency? Because בית הלל Beis Hillel says one vertebra is
removed, it doesn't cause טומאה, tuma, but then it also means that
it's a טרפה treifa by just removing one vertebra. So if it's
true that their debate also applies to טרפה, treifa, then we should
have said that בית הלל Beis Hillel is strict, one vertebra already
makes it a טרפה. treifa. So the debate really was with טומאה.
tuma. That's what the גמרא Gemara says. גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה
רבא, amar lei Rava, כי אקשי לעניין טומאה אקשי, ki akshi leinyan
tuma akshi,
when the question was originally raised, it was raised relating to the
טומאה tuma of the human skeleton. So there, in that case, that
would be בית שמאי לחומרא, Beis Shammai lechumra, בית שמאי Beis Shammai
was strict. בית שמאי Beis Shammai says it still creates טומאה tuma
until you remove two ribs in a tent, and בית הלל Beis
Hillel says it stops having טומאה tuma as soon as you remove
one, not rib, excuse me, vertebra. We just then said that the
same thing could derive and apply that to questions of טרפה treifa
and then their positions would reverse, who would be strict who would
be stringent. But originally the way it was framed, בית שמאי Beis
Shammai was strict and בית הלל Beis Hillel was lenient, yes.
Another example of a stringency creating leniency.
Exactly. This actually is the classic example about also being consistent in
your פסק, psak, that you don't rule if you rule one way
about the skeleton and אוהל, ohel, you can't rule the other way,
you can't be strict both ways and don't be lenient both ways,
be consistent.
Okay, now
what does one have to do with the other?
The assumption is that it's not considered a full representation of a
human, like a human skeleton, if a human couldn't live with it
absent, and therefore because of that, it also creates a טרפה treifa
because we assume that if a human couldn't live an animal can't
live. But you're right, there are a lot of assumptions there.
So if a skeleton was missing a finger, it'd be okay. Correct.
These are specifically the vertebrae, right. Okay. All right,
so now we're going to go on to this list of additional
טרפות: treifas: וגולגולת שנחבסה ברובה, vegulgoles shenichbesa beruba, the majority of it's
bashed in, but again not exactly cracked because that's a different issue.
So בעי רמי בר אמי: baei Rami bar Ami: רוב גובהה או
רוב היקפה, rov govha o rov heikeifa, the majority of the height
of the skull or of the circumference. So רש"י Rashi says the
circumference is bigger than the height. I'm not exactly sure I'm getting
this because isn't the majority of the... because maybe if it's... I
don't get the math about that. I mean if the majority of
the circumference means like you go down the middle here when you
go all the way around this way, right, and the majority of
the height, by the way רש"י Rashi says where's the majority of
the height? רש"י Rashi says we assume like the nose, right? רש"י
Rashi says the eyes of, if you've ever learned about drawing a
human face, they say you make an oval, you split it, you
know, you make a line down both sides and the midline is
where you draw the eyes. We normally, I think, at least me,
you normally think the eyes are high and the nose is in
the middle, but actually technically the eyes are at the midpoint of
the skull. So anyway רש"י Rashi says
it's about the face opposed to the head.
Oh, maybe that's it, because you don't count like the hair, you
start thinking about like where you start focusing on the face, you
focus on the eyes, right, but the whole thing. Anyway, so רש"י
Rashi says the eyes above. I guess
if it's half-half, maybe because it's not a perfect sphere, but if
it's not a perfect sphere, doesn't it get narrower on the
bottom? So shouldn't this half be more if it's the eyes up
because
it's
bigger at the top part?
Yeah, it does mean circumference this way, but it's circumference presumably the
whole circumference? I don't know. Anyway, somehow it makes a difference. You
can go ahead and do some tests with eggs and figure it
out. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says: תיקו, teiku, we don't know.
Okay, the question was what?
If it's when we say the majority of the head crashed in,
how do you measure majority? Okay, so I mean we would just
say surface area, I would think. Yeah, I'm not getting it. Okay,
ובשר החופה רוב הכרס ברובו. uvasar hachofeh rov hakeres beruba. Now also
if it is this is literally the flesh that covers the majority
of the כרס, keres, the rumen stomach, but that's basically the abdominal
muscle that runs underneath the rumen. So in that case if the
majority of it is torn or removed or whatever, that's another טרפה.
treifa. So that's a new
addition.
So בעי רב אשי: baei Rav Ashi: ברוב קרוע או ברוב נטול,
berov karua o berov natul, do we mean most of this muscle
is torn, right, so it's just a tear that goes down the
majority, or do we mean most of it is removed? move, which
is a much bigger leniency. Okay, so תפשוט ליה מדתנן, tifshalei miditnan,
learn it out from the משנה. Mishna. What does the משנה Mishna
say? כרס הפנימית שניקבה או שנקרעה רוב החיצונה: kersa hapnimis shenikva o
shenikra rov hachitzona:
the inner rumen had a hole, or the outer rumen, right, was
torn, the majority torn. Now, what is this outer rumen? So ואמרי
במערבא, ve'amri bama'arava, in Eretz Yisrael they say משמיה דרבי יוחנן בר
חנינא, mishmeih de'Rabbi Yochanan bar Chanina, כל הכרס כולה זו היא כרס
הפנימית: kol hakers kula zo hi kers hapnimis:
the entire כרס kers is the inner one. ואיזו היא כרס החיצונה,
ve'eizo hi kers hachitzona, what is the outer one? It's not really
part of the stomach. It means the thing on the outside of
the stomach. זהו בשר החופה את רוב הכרס: zehu basar hachofeh es
rov hakers: that is exactly, exactly this abdominal muscle. So according to
that read of the משנה, Mishna, what שמואל Shmuel is saying is
not the is exactly the משנה. Mishna. What שמואל Shmuel is saying
is the case of the outer stomach, the thing on the outside
of the stomach, and there it's explicit that majority means torn, the
majority of it is torn. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
מיהו טעמיה דשמואל, mihu ta'ameih de'Shmuel, we're asking according to שמואל Shmuel
who introduced this, and שמואל Shmuel introduced this as a new category.
So רבי יעקב בר נחמני Rabbi Yaakov bar Nachmani אמר שמואל, amar
Shmuel, I'm sorry, I skipped a line. והאמר רבי יעקב בר נחמני
אמר שמואל, veha'amar Rabbi Yaakov bar Nachmani amar Shmuel, מקום שאין בו
מילת, makom she'ein bo milas, he explains the משנה Mishna differently. He
says that the outer
כרס kers is where the felt-like feel of the inside stops. That
for him is the outer one, and the inner one is what
do you call it? And the inner one is just the stuff
that's closer to the front of the animal, the outer one is
the stuff more to the back where the felty inside stops. So
he doesn't have the case of the abdominal muscle in the משנה.
Mishna. That was also implicit because שמואל Shmuel is basically saying I
am going to give you a new טריפה treifa not mentioned in
the משנה. Mishna. So if it's what's referred to in the משנה,
Mishna, then yes, it means the majority is torn. But if it's
not what's referred to in the משנה, Mishna, if it's a new
type of טריפה, treifa, this idea of the abdominal muscle, then we
don't know if majority means majority torn or majority removed. Okay, so
we don't have an answer. Now we are done with broken bones
and vertebrae, and we also
caved-in skull and a couple of new of the Amoraic additions, also
this question of the abdominal muscle which might have been referred to
before. And now we go on to the משנה. Mishna. So the
next thing of the משנה, Mishna, we did inner organs, we did
sort of bones, and now we are talking about something again that
is not that is not a specific thing we can identify which
organ is the problem, but is the issue about when an animal
attacks it. And we are concerned about this issue of poison. Although
as we're going to see in a later
משנה, Mishna, later משניות mishnayos have animals eating poison and they say
they're not טריפה, treifa, they say don't eat it, it's סכנת נפשות,
sakanas nefashos, but it's not טריפה. treifa. So poison itself does not
make an animal טריפה; treifa; it really needs a type of, like
I said, violence to the body. But here maybe it's the combination.
It was attacked and clawed, and that was a violence to the
body. So although the hole itself is not what makes it the
טריפה, treifa, it's the insertion of either the poison, or some people
mention the possibility we're talking about rabies or some type of infection,
which makes more sense because it talks about wolves and other animals
that don't have poison, but it's some combination of that coming through
a violence to the body, not just the infection itself.
Just so you know, if it's really rabies, then you may say
let's just you didn't see it, but you just see the animal
like going all berserk.
No, but even if you know, the משנה Mishna later is going
to be clear that if it's got an illness or poison or
whatever, that doesn't make it a טריפה. treifa. It has to be
some sense of violence. But here it's some interesting combination of the
two. So let's take a look. Okay, ודרוסת הזאב uderusas haze'ev and
being sort of trampled or clawed at by a wolf. אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב: amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav: בבהמה מן הזאב ולמעלה,
beveheima min haze'ev ulema'la, if you're talking about an animal, meaning not
birds, then the type of animal that has to attack it has
to be a wolf or a larger animal. ובעופות מן הנץ ולמעלה,
uve'ofos min hanetz ulema'la, by birds, it has to be the נץ,
netz, which I believe we said was a sparrow hawk, or larger
birds, but smaller would not be a problem. Now, that's pretty much
the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna said if a זאב ze'ev attacks
an animal or a sparrow-hawk attacks a bird. I don't know. Anyway,
למיעוטי מאי, lemayutei mai, what are you excluding? אילימא למיעוטי חתול, eileima
lemayutei chasul, something smaller than a wolf? תנינא, tanina, that's implicit in
our משנה: Mishna: ודרוסת הזאב. uderusas haze'ev. It said if it's attacked
by a wolf, meaning anything less than a wolf wouldn't be a
problem. וכי תימא הכא קמשמע לן דזאב בגסה נמי דריס, vechi teima
hacha kamoshma lan deze'ev begasa nami daris, maybe I would have thought
when the משנה Mishna says a wolf, it would have meant a
wolf for small animals like a sheep or goat, but maybe a
wolf for a cow would have been meaningless. So when he's he's
right, obviously we don't need him to tell us less than a
wolf is not a problem, but what he is telling us is
that a wolf is a problem for all animals, even including things
like cows. If that's what he's telling us, והתנן רבי יהודה אומר,
vehatnan Rabbi Yehuda omer, but it's not true, because רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says: דרוסת הזאב בדקה, drusas haze'ev bedaka, a wolf is only
if it attacks a small animal like a sheep or goat, ודרוסת
הארי בגסה, uderusas ha'ari begasa, but a large animal like a cow,
it's only if it's attacked by a lion. Okay, וכי תימא רבי
יהודה מפלג פליג, vechi teima Rabbi Yehuda miflag palig, that's רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda disagrees with the תנא קמא, Tanna
Kamma, or תנא קמא Tanna Kamma might say a wolf is sufficient
for all animals. והא רבי בנימין בר יפת אמר רבי אילא. veha
Rabbi Binyamin bar Yafes amar Rabbi Ila.
He said that רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda is just clarifying when the
חכמים Chachamim said a wolf is enough. He's not arguing then, he's
claiming that a wolf is always is only good for small animals.
So if that's true again, why do you need this statement that
you know, you go by wolf? That's explicit in the משנה. Mishna.
So the גמרא Gemara says גברא גברא קא רמית? gavra gavra ka
ramit? What, how you asked from one opinion to another opinion? This
opinion says רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda is only coming to clarify. He
would be of the opinion רב יהודה אמר רב Rav Yehuda amar
Rav would be of the opinion that רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda is
disagreeing, and that's exactly what he's coming to say. רבי יהודה Rabi
Yehuda says by large animals you need a lion, I am
telling you that by all large animals, by all animals, whether they're
goats or sheep or cows, a wolf is nothing less than a
wolf, but you also don't need anything more than a wolf. A
wolf is you know, the minimum that you need and you know,
you don't need more you don't need less. A wolf by all
animals. So that's exactly what he's coming to tell you, not like
this, that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma disagrees with רבי יהודה. Rabi
Yehuda. So the גמרא Gemara says that's one answer. ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'it
eima, if you want, לעולם למעוטי חתול. l'olam l'miuti chatul. He really
is saying wolf to tell you less than a wolf is no
good. Even a cat would not be good. So מהו דתימא, mahu
d'teima, אורחא דמילתא קתני, orcha d'milta katani, when it said wolf, I
might have thought, you know, again we're talking now within even small
animals like sheep and goat. It's just telling you the most common
thing that would attack sheep and goat would be a wolf, but
maybe even smaller animals would also be a problem like cats. קא
משמע לן ka mashma lan that no, that he means specifically, only
a wolf. So now what have we said? We said the משנה
Mishna says wolf, it means specifically nothing smaller than a wolf. Would
it also be a wolf for large animals? Is the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma disagreeing with רבי יהודה? Rabi Yehuda? Two opinions. Okay.
Now
what animals are smaller than wolves that will attack larger
animals and maybe even more viciously? Right, I know. So again the
question of do we just mean size is also unclear. Now we're
going to deal with a couple more animals. Let's just read a
little bit more. אמר רב עמרם אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Amram
amar Rav Chisda, דרוסת חתול ונמייה, drusat chatul u'nemiyah,
if you have the clawing of a cat or a נמייה—how nemiyah
do they translate נמייה? nemiyah? Weasel? Weasel, that's probably right. Marten,
so that explains it. Okay, בכבשים וגדיים, bi'kvashim u'gedayim, if it's against
goats and kids, you know, kid goats and baby sheep. So now
we're not just dealing with small species, but we're talking about the
babies, the small ones. So that would be sufficient. It's by the
large versions of an adult sheep or goat, you need a wolf.
By a baby sheep or goat, it's enough to have a cat.
Okay, so it's not only the species, it's the size of the
attacked animal. דרוסת חולדה, drusat chuldah, if it's a weasel, בעופות, b'ofot,
that's also sufficient, that is a problem by birds. מיתיבי, meitivei, I'll
ask on this: דרוסת חתול נץ ונמייה, drusat chatul netz u'nemiyah, if
it's attacked by a cat, a נץ, netz, or this נמייה, nemiyah,
עד שתנקב לחלל, ad she'tinakev l'chalal, that is only—that is not a
problem in itself. It's only a problem if it causes a piercing
of an inner organ. But just the attack of these things themselves
without piercing an inner organ is not a problem. So here you
have this entire list that you just told me sometimes is a
problem and we say here it's not a problem. אבל דרוסה לית
להו, aval drusa leit lehu, but דרוסה drusa it says explicitly in
this list is not a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says back,
one minute. ותסברא, v'tisbra, does that make sense? נץ לא דריס, netz
lo daris, do you really mean a נץ netz does not do
דרוסה? drusa? והא תנן, v'ha tnan, our משנה Mishna says: ודרוסת הנץ.
u'drusat ha'netz. It includes the נץ netz by birds. הא לא קשיא,
ha lo kashya, כאן בעוף כאן בגדיים וטלאים. kan b'of kan bi'gedayim
u'tlayim.
That's not a problem. I could say the נץ netz is a
problem by birds, but this list of animals that don't do דרוסה
drusa is maybe by—against other animals. Okay, מכל מקום לרב חסדא קשיא,
mikol makom l'Rav Chisda kashya, we've got a problem. So what's the
problem? We have a list that נץ, netz,
cats, and נמיות nemiyot don't do דרוסה drusa presumably against other
animals. But רב חסדא Rav Chisda said they can do an act
of דרוסה drusa against, you know, baby goats, baby sheep. So how
did this list say that they never do
דרוסה? drusa? הוא דאמר כי האי תנא, hu d'amar ki hai tanna,
he says like the following תנא. tanna. דתניא, d'tanya, ברבי אומר, Birebbi
omer, ברבי Birebbi says: לא אמרו אין דרוסה אלא במקום שאין מצילים.
lo amru ein drusa ela b'makom she'ein matzilim. When did these things
not create דרוסה, drusa, these animals in this list? When
they're
not—the animals are not afraid, the attacking animals are not afraid that
there's going to be—somebody's going to intervene and save their prey. So
if they're not afraid that somebody's going to intervene and save their
prey, they won't attack it in a vicious way or with poison
or whatever that will cause the דרוסה drusa problem. אבל במקום שיש
מצילים, aval b'makom she'yesh matzilim, if the attacking animals are afraid that
something is going to intervene and save their prey, then they're going
to be more vicious or quicker about their attack and it will—the
act of attacking will create a problem. Then in that case, יש
דרוסה, yesh drusa, there is דרוסה. drusa. ובמקום שאין מצילים, u'b'makom she'ein
matzilim, okay, so we'll pick up with this tomorrow, but the basic
answer is what? is that yes you said that there was דרוסה
derusa by these things like cats and weasels etcetera by at least
small animals. We said there isn't, so the difference is whether the
attacking animal thinks it's going to be there'll be an inter- you
know where the prey will be saved. If it thinks the prey
will be saved, it'll be more vicious and it will be able
to attack that prey and it will you know in a harsher
way and there's a problem of דרוסה. derusa. If it doesn't think,
if it thinks it's safe and protected, we don't have a דרוסה
derusa problem. Yes, so all this is quite fascinating because what the
heck is it talking about with poison and what not?
The only thing that makes sense is it would be rabies and
that any warm-blooded animal can have rabies.
Does it smoke in there or do they have some neon over
there or what? Why is it whether intervening will be a problem
or not also is
a